<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" 
          "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">


<article id="index">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Life with Adeos</title>
    <releaseinfo>Revision B</releaseinfo>
    <pubdate>10/09/2005</pubdate>
    <author>
      <firstname>Philippe</firstname>
      <surname>Gerum</surname>	
    </author>
    <copyright>
      <year>2005</year>
    </copyright>

    <abstract>
      <para>This article gives an overview of the Adeos technology and
      what it provides to Xenomai. After an introduction addressing
      the event pipeline, the implementation of interrupts dispatching
      as well as the system event propagation, we will then study the
      interactions between Xenomai and Adeos. The notions of primary
      and secondary domains will be explained and we will also be
      interested in studying how interrupts get propagated. We will
      finally conclude on a few tips and tricks to disable/enable
      interrupts sources and to share interrupts between domains.
      </para>
    </abstract>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Copyright &copy; 2005 Philippe Gerum</para>
      <para>
	Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
	document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation
	License, Version 1.2 or any later version published by the
	Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, no
	Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.  A copy of the
	license is published on gnu.org: <ulink
	url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/fdl.html">"GNU Free
	Documentation License"</ulink>.
      </para>
    </legalnotice>
</articleinfo>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ===                      WHAT IS ADEOS                       ==== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->

  <sect1 id="What_is_Adeos" xreflabel="what is adeos">
    <title>What is Adeos</title>

    <para>Adeos is a resource virtualization layer available as a
      Linux kernel patch, which general design has been proposed by
      <emphasis>Karim Yaghmour</emphasis> in a technical paper, back in
      2001.</para>

    <para>The current incarnation of this proposal makes it a simple, yet
      efficient real-time system enabler, providing a mean to run a regular
      GNU/Linux environment and a RTOS, side-by-side on the same
      hardware.</para> 

    <para>To this end, Adeos enables multiple
      entities&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;called domains&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;to
      exist simultaneously on the same machine. These domains do not
      necessarily see each other, but all of them see Adeos. A domain is
      most probably a complete OS, but there is no assumption being made
      regarding the sophistication of what is in a domain. However, all
      domains are likely to compete for processing external events
      (e.g. interrupts) or internal ones (e.g. traps, exceptions),
      according to the system-wide priority they have been given.</para> 
 
    <para>Additionally to its straightforward virtualization capabilities,
      another key advantage of Adeos relies in its ability to export a
      generic API to client domains, which does not depend on the CPU
      architecture. Therefore, much if not most of the porting effort for
      client domains occurs at the Adeos level.</para>

    <!-- ===                   The event pipeline                    === -->

    <sect2 id="The_event_pipeline" xreflabel="event pipeline">
      <title>The event pipeline</title>

      <para>The fundamental Adeos structure one must keep in mind is the
	chain of client domains asking for event control. A domain is a
	kernel-based software component which can ask the Adeos layer to be
	notified of:
	
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Every incoming external interrupt, or auto-generated
	      virtual interrupt;</para>
	  </listitem> 
	  <listitem><para>Every system call issued by Linux
	      applications,</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Other system events triggered by the kernel code
	      (e.g. Linux task switching, signal notification, Linux task exits
	      etc.)</para></listitem> 
	</itemizedlist></para>
      
      <para>Adeos ensures that events are dispatched in an orderly manner
	to the various client domains according to their respective
	priority in the system, so it is possible to provide for timely and
	predictable delivery of such events. This is achieved by assigning
	each domain a static priority. This priority value strictly defines
	the delivery order of events to the domains. All active domains are
	queued according to their respective priority, forming the pipeline
	abstraction used by Adeos to make the events flow, from the highest
	to the lowest priority domain. Incoming events (including
	interrupts) are pushed to the head of the pipeline (i.e. to the
	highest priority domain) and progress down to its tail
	(i.e. to the lowest priority domain). The figure below gives a
	general view of some Adeos-based system, where multiple
	domains are sharing events through the pipeline abstraction:</para>

      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject role="html">
	  <imagedata format="JPG"
	             align="center"
	             valign="middle"
	             fileref="life-with-adeos-img1.jpg"/>
	</imageobject>
	<caption>
	  <para>
	    Event pipeline representation
	  </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>In the figure above, the position of the Linux kernel with
	respect to the pipelining order might be anywhere; this said, the
	Linux kernel still has a special role since it stands for the root
	domain, because all other domains need Linux to install them,
	usually by mean of loading the kernel modules which embody
	them.</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- ===             Optimistic interrupt protection             === -->

    <sect2 id="Optimistic_interrupt_protection" xreflabel="optimistic
      interrupt protection">
      <title>Optimistic interrupt protection</title>

      <para>In order to dispatch interrupts in an prioritized manner,
      while still allowing domains to create interrupt-free sections,
      Adeos implements the so-called <emphasis>Optimistic interrupt
      protection scheme</emphasis> as described by Stodolsky, Chen,
      and Bershad, <ulink
      url="http://citeseer.nj.nec.com/stodolsky93fast.html">in the
      following paper.</ulink></para>

      <para>The stage of the pipeline occupied by any given domain can
      be <emphasis>stalled</emphasis>, which means that the next
      incoming interrupt will not be delivered to the domain's
      handler, and will be prevented from flowing down to the lowest
      priority domain(s) in the same move. While a stage is stalled,
      pending interrupts accumulate in the domain's interrupt log, and
      eventually get played when the stage is
      <emphasis>unstalled</emphasis>, by an internal operation called
      synchronization. Domains use this feature to protect their own
      critical sections from unwanted preemption by their own
      interrupt handlers. However, thanks to the virtualization of the
      interrupt control Adeos brings, a higher priority domain can
      still receive interrupts, and eventually preempt any lower
      priority domain. Practically, this means that, albeit an
      Adeos-enabled Linux kernel regularly stalls its own stage to
      perform critical operations, a real-time system running ahead of
      it in the pipeline would still be able to receive interrupts any
      time, with no incurred delay.</para>

      <para>When a domain has finished processing all the pending
      interrupts it has received, it then calls a special Adeos
      service which yields the CPU to the next domain down the
      pipeline, so the latter can process in turn the pending events
      it has been notified of, and this cycle continues down to the
      lowest priority domain of the pipeline.</para>

      <para>The figure below illustrates how several domains running
      on mutiple CPUs can share the incoming interrupts through the
      Adeos pipeline abstraction. Of course, a correct book-keeping of
      pending interrupts must be done while a stage is stalled: this
      is achieved by a per-domain, per-CPU interrupt log, as
      illustrated below:</para>

      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject role="html">
	  <imagedata format="JPG"
	             align="center"
	             valign="middle"
	             fileref="life-with-adeos-img2.jpg"/>
	</imageobject>
	<caption>
	  <para>
	    The optimistic interrupt protection scheme
	  </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>

    </sect2>

    <!-- ===                System event propagation                 === -->

    <sect2 id="System-event_propagation" xreflabel="system event propagation">
      <title>System-event propagation</title>

      <para>Interrupts are not the only kind of events which can flow
      through the pipeline abstraction; internal events triggered by
      the Linux kernel itself or its applications can generate what is
      called system events. Basically, system events are synchronous
      notifications of trap, exception, or some action performed by
      the Linux kernel, and which gets notified to any interested
      parties through the pipeline.</para>

      <para>Since those events are synchronous by essence, there is no
      way to defer their notification through the stall operation,
      just because you cannot delay their handling. The rationale
      behind such design decision comes from the fact that a code
      triggering a system event might just not be able to continue
      without immediate intervention from the corresponding handler:
      e.g. the page fault handler must run immediately upon memory
      addressing exception, delaying it makes no sense. In other
      words, stall/unstall operations on any given domain only concern
      interrupts, either real or virtual.</para>

    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ===           WHAT DOES ADEOS PROVIDE TO XENOMAI ?           ==== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->

  <sect1 id="What_does_Adeos_provide_to_Xenomai" xreflabel="what does
    adeos provide">
    <title>What does Adeos provide to Xenomai?</title>

    <para>Conversely, this question could also be: <emphasis>what
    basic guarantees does Xenomai need to provide real-time
    services?</emphasis> The answer is simple and straightforward: it
    must be allowed to handle all incoming interrupts first, before
    the Linux kernel has had the opportunity to notice them, and it
    must be able to handle them <emphasis>immediately</emphasis>,
    regardless of any current attempt from the Linux kernel to lock
    them out using the CPU interrupt mask. It must also make sure to
    always enforce the proper priority management for its threads,
    regardless of their current execution domain.</para>

    <para>These guarantees give Xenomai predictable interrupt
    latencies in the lowest micro-second level range whatever activity
    Linux is undergoing, which once coupled with Xenomai's fast
    co-scheduling technique of Linux tasks (i.e. shadow threading),
    provide for deterministic scheduling latencies of real-time
    threads. The figure below illustrates the position of the Adeos
    layer in the Xenomai architecture:</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
	<imagedata format="JPG"
	  align="center"
	  valign="middle"
	  fileref="life-with-adeos-img3.jpg"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
	<para>
	  Position of Adeos in the Xenomai architecture
	</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>You will notice that the Adeos interface is directly exposed
    to the Hardware Abstraction Layer which underlies the Xenomai
    core.  Therefore, most of the requests for Adeos services are
    issued from the HAL, which implementation can be found in the
    relevant <filename>arch/&lt;archname&gt;/hal</filename>
    directories, the generic bits being available under
    <filename>arch/generic/hal</filename>. Having a look at the latter
    is the best approach to understand howXenomai makes use of Adeos
    for its own purposes.</para>

    <!-- ===      Xenomai's primary and secondary domain             === -->

    <sect2 id="Xenomai_primary_and_secondary_domain"
      xreflabel="primary and secondary domain">
      <title>Xenomai's primary and secondary domains</title>

      <para>Xenomai allows to run real-time threads either strictly in
      kernel space, or within the address space of a Linux process. In
      the rest of this article, we will refer to the latter as the
      Xenomai threads, not to be confused with regular Linux tasks
      (even when they belong to the <literal>SCHED_FIFO</literal>
      class). All threads managed by Xenomai are known from the
      real-time nucleus.</para>

      <para>Support for real-time threads exclusively running in
      kernel space is a reminiscence of the mere co-kernel era, before
      the advent of true real-time support in user-space, when
      real-time applications would only run embodied into kernel
      modules; this feature has been kept in Xenomai mainly for the
      purpose of supporting legacy applications, and won't be
      discussed here.</para>

      <para>What is more interesting is that Xenomai has a symbiotic
      approach with respect to Linux; this is, for instance, what
      makes it different from the RTAI/LXRT implementation. To this
      end, Xenomai threads are not only able to run over the context
      of the highest priority domain in the pipeline (i.e. the primary
      domain) like kernel-based Xenomai threads, but also in the
      regular Linux space (i.e. the secondary domain), while still
      being considered as real-time by Xenomai, albeit suffering
      higher scheduling latencies.  In Xenomai's jargon, the former
      are said to run in primary execution mode, whilst the latter
      undergo the secondary execution mode.</para>

      <para>In order to provide a complete real-time support to
      threads running in the secondary domain, Xenomai needs the
      following to be achieved:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para><emphasis>Common priority scheme</emphasis>.
	  Scheduling-wise, we need a way to have both the real- time
	  nucleus and the Linux kernel share the same priority scheme
	  with respect to the set of threads they share the control
	  of; in other words, a Xenomai thread should have its
	  priority properly enforced at any time, regardless of its
	  current domain, among all existing Xenomai threads. Xenomai
	  applies what it calls the root thread's mutable priority
	  technique, by which the Linux kernel automatically inherits
	  the priority of the Xenomai thread controlled by the
	  real-time nucleus which happens to enter the secondary
	  domain.  Practically, this means that Xenomai threads
	  currently running in the primary domain won't necessarily
	  preempt those running in the secondary one, unless their
	  effective priority is actually higher.  The above behaviour
	  is to be opposed to what happens with RTAI/LXRT for
	  instance, where threads migrating to the Linux space
	  actually lose their real-time priority in the same move, by
	  inheriting the lowest priority defined by the RTAI
	  scheduler. This said, regular Linux tasks unknown to
	  Xenomai, and which only happen to belong to the SCHED_FIFO
	  class, will always be preempted when competing for the CPU
	  with Xenomai threads from the primary Xenomai domain, albeit
	  they will still compete priority-wise with Xenomai threads
	  running in the secondary domain.</para></listitem>
	
	<listitem><para><emphasis>Predictability of program execution
	times</emphasis>. When a Xenomai thread runs over the Linux
	(i.e. secondary) domain, either executing kernel or
	application code, its timing should not be perturbated by non
	real-time Linux interrupt activities, and generally speaking,
	by any, low priority, asynchronous activity occurring at
	kernel level. A simple way to prevent most opportunities for
	the latter to happen is to starve the Linux kernel from
	interrupts when a Xenomai thread is running in the Linux
	domain, so that no deferred post-processing could be triggered
	from top-halves interrupt handlers during this period of
	time. A simple way to starve the Linux kernel from interrupts
	is to block them when needed inside an intermediate Adeos
	domain, sitting between those occupied by the real-time
	nucleus and the Linux kernel, which is called the interrupt
	shield in Xenomai's jargon.  This shield is engaged whenever a
	Xenomai thread is scheduled in by the Linux kernel, and
	disengaged in all other cases. It should be noted that the
	shielding support can be enabled/disabled on a per-thread
	basis, or on a system-wide basis at Xenomai build time; by
	default, it is disabled for Xenomai threads and not built
	in.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para><emphasis>Fine-grained Linux
	kernel</emphasis>. In order to get the best from the secondary
	execution mode, we need the Linux kernel to exhibit the
	shortest possible non-preemptible section, so that
	rescheduling opportunities are taken as soon as possible after
	a Xenomai thread running in the secondary domain becomes
	ready-to-run. Additionally, this ensures that Xenomai threads
	can migrate from the primary to the secondary domain within a
	short and time-bounded period of time, since this operation
	involves reaching a kernel rescheduling point. For this
	reason, Xenomai benefits from the continuous trend of
	improvements regarding the overall preemptibility of the Linux
	kernel, including Ingo Molnar's PREEMPT_RT extension. Of
	course, Xenomai threads which only run in the primary domain
	are not impacted by the level of granularity of the Linux
	kernel, and always benefit from ultra-low and bounded
	latencies, since they do not need to synchonize in any way
	with the undergoing Linux operations, which they actually
	always preempt unconditionally.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para><emphasis>Priority inversion
	management.</emphasis> Both the real-time nucleus and the
	Linux kernel should handle the case where a high priority
	thread is kept from running because a low priority one holds a
	contended resource for a possibly unbounded amount of
	time. Xenomai provides this support, but only the PREEMPT_RT
	variant does so for the Linux kernel. For this reason, Xenomai
	keeps an eye and provides support for the current developments
	of PREEMPT_RT, albeit the mainline kernel still remains the
	system of reference for now.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>As a consequence of the requirements above, when the
      Xenomai core is loaded, the underlying Adeos pipeline contains
      three stages, through which all interrupts are flowing, by order
      of priority:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Xenomai's primary domain, which is the home of the
	  real-time nucleus;</para></listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>The interrupt shield domain;</para></listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>The Linux domain.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject role="html">
	  <imagedata format="JPG"
	    align="center"
	    valign="middle"
	    fileref="life-with-adeos-img4.jpg"/>
	</imageobject>
	<caption>
	  <para>
	    The three stages of the Adeos pipeline
	  </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>


    </sect2>


    <!-- ===                System call interception                 === -->

    <sect2 id="System_call_interception" xreflabel="system call interception">
      <title>System call interception</title>
      
      <para>Since real-time APIs (i.e. skins) which are stackable over
      the Xenomai nucleus, can export their own set of services to
      Xenomai threads in user-space, there must be a way to properly
      dispatch the corresponding system calls, and the regular Linux
      kernel system calls altogether, to the proper handlers. To this
      end, Xenomai intercepts every system call trap/exception issued
      on behalf of any of the Xenomai or Linux domains by the Xenomai
      threads. This is made possible by subscribing an event handler
      using the proper Adeos service (for more on this, see the
      <command>adeos_catch_event()</command> service, when specifying
      the
      <literal>ADEOS_SYSCALL_PROLOGUE/IPIPE_EVENT_SYSCALL</literal>
      event). Xenomai uses this capability to:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Dispatch the real-time services requests from
	applications to the proper system call handlers, which are
	implemented by the various APIs running over the real-time
	nucleus;</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Ensure that every system call is performed
	under the control of the proper domain, either Xenomai or
	Linux, by migrating the caller seamlessly to the target domain
	as required. For instance, a Linux system call issued from a
	Xenomai thread running in the Xenomai domain will cause the
	automatic migration of the caller to the Linux domain, before
	the request is relayed to the regular Linux system call
	handler. Conversely, a Xenomai thread which invokes a possibly
	blocking Xenomai system call will be moved to the Xenomai
	domain before the service is eventually performed, so that the
	caller may sleep under the control of the real-time
	nucleus.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The combination of both makes Xenomai threads particularly
      well integrated into the Linux realm. For instance, a common
      system call path for Xenomai and the regular Linux applications
      makes the former appear as a natural extension of the latter. As
      an illustration of this, Xenomai threads both support the full
      Linux signals semantics and ptracing feature, which in turn
      enables the GDB support natively for them.</para>

    </sect2>

    <!-- ===                 Interrupt propagation                   === -->

    <sect2 id="Interrupt_propagatio">
      <title>Interrupt propagation</title>

      <para>Because it is ahead in the pipeline, the real-time nucleus
      which lives in the Xenomai domain is first notified of any
      incoming interrupt of interest, processes it, then marks such
      interrupt to be passed down the pipeline, eventually to the
      Linux kernel domain, if needed.</para>

      <para>When notified from an incoming interrupt, the real-time
      nucleus reschedules after the outer interrupt handler has
      returned (in case interrupts are piling up), and switches in the
      highest priority runnable thread it controls.</para>

      <para>The Xenomai domain yields the CPU to the interrupt shield
      domain when no real-time activity is pending, which in turn let
      them through whenever it is disengaged to the Linux kernel, or
      block them if engaged. Adeos has two basic propagation modes for
      interrupts through the pipeline:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>In the implicit mode, any incoming interrupt
	is automatically marked as pending by Adeos into each and
	every receiving domain's log accepting the interrupt
	source.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>In the explicit mode, an interrupt must be
	propagated "manually" if needed by the interrupt handler to
	the neighbour domain down the pipeline.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>This setting is defined on a per-domain, per-interrupt
      basis.  Xenomai always uses the explicit mode for all interrupts
      it intercepts. This means that each handler must call the
      explicit propagation service to pass an incoming interrupt down
      the pipeline. When no handler is defined for a given interrupt
      by Xenomai, the interrupt is unconditionally propagated down to
      the Linux kernel: this keeps the system working when the
      real-time nucleus does not intercept such interrupt.</para>

    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ===                        TIPS AND TRICKS                   ==== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->

<sect1 id="Tips_and_trick" xreflabel="tips and tricks">
    <title>Tips and tricks</title>

    <!-- ===          Enabling Disabling it source                   === -->

    <sect2 id="Enabling_Disabling_interrupt_source" xreflabel="enabling
      disabling it source">
      <title>Enabling/Disabling interrupt sources</title>

      <para>In addition to being able to stall a domain entirely so
      that no interrupt could flow through it anymore until it is
      explicitly unstalled, Adeos allows to selectively disable, and
      conversely re-enable, the actual source of interrupts, at
      hardware level.</para>

      <para>After having taken over the box, Adeos handles the
      interrupt disabling requests for all domains, including for the
      Linux kernel and the real-time nucleus. This means disabling the
      interrupt source at the hardware PIC level, and locking out any
      interrupt delivery from this source to the current domain at the
      pipeline level. Conversely, enabling interrupts means
      reactivating the interrupt source at the PIC level, and allowing
      further delivery from this source to the current
      domain. Therefore, a domain enabling an interrupt source must be
      the same as the one which disabled it, because such operation is
      domain-dependent.</para>

      <para>Practically, this means that, when used in pair, the
      <literal>rthal_irq_disable()</literal> and
      <literal>rthal_irq_enable()</literal> services which encapsulate
      the relevant Adeos calls inside the real-time HAL underlying
      Xenomai, must be issued from the same Adeos domain. For
      instance, if a real-time interrupt handler connected to some
      interrupt source using the
      <literal>rthal_irq_request()</literal> service, disables the
      source using rthal_irq_disable(), then such source will be
      blocked for the Xenomai domain until
      <literal>rthal_irq_enable()</literal> is called for the same
      interrupt, and from the same domain. Failing to deal with this
      requirement usually leads to the permanent loss of the affected
      interrupt channel.</para>
    </sect2>

    <!-- ===           Sharing it between domains                    === -->

    <sect2 id="Sharing_interrupts_between_domain" xreflabel="sharing
      it between domains">
      <title>Sharing interrupts between domains</title>

      <para>A typical example of mis-using the Adeos pipeline when
      sharing hardware interrupts between domains is as
      follows:</para>
 
      <programlisting>
void realtime_eth_handler (unsigned irq, void *cookie) 
{ 
    /* 
     * This interrupt handler has been installed using 
     * rthal_irq_request(), so it will always be invoked on behalf of 
     * the Xenomai (primary) domain. 
     */ 

    rthal_irq_disable(irq); 
    /* The Xenomai domain won't receive this irq anymore */
    
    rthal_irq_host_pend(irq); 
    /* This irq has been marked as pending for Linux */ 
}

void linux_eth_handler (int irq, void *dev_id, struct pt_regs *regs) 
{ 
    /* 
     * This interrupt handler has been installed using 
     * rthal_irq_host_request(), so it will always be invoked on 
     * behalf of the Linux (secondary) domain, as a shared interrupt 
     * handler (Linux-wise). 
     */ 
    rthal_irq_enable(irq); 
    
    /* 
     * BUG: This won't work as expected: we are only unlocking the 
     * interrupt source for the Linux domain which is current here, 
     * not for the Xenomai domain! 
     */ 
      </programlisting>

      <para>In the non-working example above, since Xenomai always
      uses the explicit propagation mode for all interrupts it
      intercepts, the next ethernet interrupt will be marked as
      pending in the Xenomai log only, waiting for the Xenomai handler
      to possibly propagate it manually down to Linux. But since the
      interrupt is still locked at pipeline level for Xenomai
      (remember that nobody actually issued the expected
      <literal>rthal_irq_enable()</literal> from the Xenomai domain,
      but only mistakenly from the Linux one), this won't happen,
      because the Xenomai handler won't run until the lock is removed.
      Therefore, well, chicken&shy;and&shy;egg problem: we are
      toast.</para>

      <para>Fortunately, there is a solution for sharing interrupts
      properly, between domains which need to keep the interrupt
      source disabled until the final processing is done (e.g. dealing
      with level-triggered interrupts is one of those issues):
      actually, you don't need to do anything, because Adeos already
      masks any incoming interrupts at PIC level before feeding the
      pipeline with it.  Therefore, you only need to process the
      interrupt as you see fit in the relevant domain handler, and
      make sure to re-enable the interrupt source from the last one
      using <literal>rthal_irq_enable()</literal>. Whenever the Linux
      kernel is one of those recipients, the regular kernel handler
      will do this re-enabling automatically, so basically, you just
      need to bother calling <literal>rthal_irq_enable()</literal> in
      handlers which don't propagate the incoming interrupts
      downstream to the Linux kernel.</para>

      <para>Specifically on the x86 architecture, it happens that the
      timer interrupt is not being masked upon receipt by Adeos, for
      performances reasons. This said, the timer source is not one you
      may want to disable in any way, so this is a
      non&shy;issue.</para>
    </sect2>


    <!-- ===         Interrupt Sharing and latency                   === -->

    <sect2 id="Interrupt_sharing_and_latency" xreflabel="it
      sharing and latency">
      <title>Interrupt sharing and latency</title>

      <para>However, keeping an interrupt source masked while the
      propagation takes place through the entire pipeline may increase
      the latency.</para>

      <para>Since Adeos guarantees that no stack overflow can occur
      due to interrupts piling up over any given domain, and because
      it also stalls the current stage before firing an interrupt
      handler, there is no need to disable the interrupt source in the
      Xenomai handler.  Instead you may even want to re-enable it, so
      that further occurrences can be immediately logged, and will get
      played immediately after the current handler invocation
      returns.</para>

      <para>So, the solution is to re-write the previous example this
      way, this time properly:</para>

      <programlisting>
void realtime_eth_handler (unsigned irq, void *cookie) 
{ 
    rthal_irq_enable(irq); 
    rthal_irq_host_pend(irq); 
    /* This irq has been marked as pending for Linux */ 
}

void linux_eth_handler (int irq, void *dev_id, struct pt_regs *regs) 
{ 
    /* process the IRQ normally. */ 
} 
      </programlisting>

    </sect2>
    
  </sect1>


  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ===                           CONCLUSION                     ==== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->

  <sect1 id="Conclusion" xreflabel="conclusion">
    <title>Conclusion</title>

    <para>Adeos is a rather simple piece of code, with very
    interesting properties when used properly. The backbone of the
    Adeos scheme is the event pipeline, and as such, it brings all the
    critical features we need in Xenomai:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>Predictable interrupt latencies;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Precise interrupt virtualization control (per-domain and
	  per-interrupt handler registration, per-domain and per-cpu
	  interrupt masking);</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Uniform, prioritized and domain-oriented propagation
	  scheme for events;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>A generic and straightforward API to ease portability of
	  client code.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Xenomai uses these features to seek the best possible
    integration of the real-time services it brings with the Linux
    kernel. Xenomai's primary mode delivers true real-time
    performances in the lowest micro-second latency
    range. Additionally, Xenomai bets on future evolutions of Linux,
    like PREEMPT_RT, to improve the kernel's overall granularity, so
    that the secondary mode will still be real-time in the
    deterministic sense, with bounded albeit higher worst-case
    latencies. This is the reason why Xenomai is working hard since
    day one to reach a tight integration level with the Linux
    kernel. Think symbiotic, seek mutualism.</para>

</sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ===                      USEFUL LINKS                        ==== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->

  <sect1 id="Useful_links" xreflabel="useful links">
    <title>Useful links</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Karim Yaghmour's Adeos proposal:
	  <ulink url="http://www.opersys.com/ftp/pub/Adeos/adeos.pdf">http://www.opersys.com/ftp/pub/Adeos/adeos.pdf</ulink></para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Optimistic Interrupt Protection:
	  <ulink url="http://citeseer.nj.nec.com/stodolsky93fast.html">http://citeseer.nj.nec.com/stodolsky93fast.html</ulink></para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>The Adeos project workspace on GNA:
	  <ulink url="https://gna.org/projects/adeos/">https://gna.org/projects/adeos/</ulink></para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Where to download the latest Adeos patches:
	  <ulink url="http://download.gna.org/adeos/patches/">http://download.gna.org/adeos/patches/</ulink></para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>The Adeos API reference manual:
	  <ulink url="http://home.gna.org/adeos/doc/api/globals.html">http://home.gna.org/adeos/doc/api/globals.html</ulink></para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

</article>
